

John K. Barrera C johnkevinbarrera@gmail.com (+51) 967016935

jkbarrera 🛅

John Barrera 📢

johnkevinbarrera 🗘

illarek.github.io

John Kevin Barrera Contreras

Data Engineer • Data Scientist • Statistician

Bachelor of Systems Engineering and student of Mathematical Statistics, with knowledge in IT, statistics, Big Data, Machine Learning, Blockchain, IoT and the development of web applications and mobile applications. I have experience in banking, telecommunications, research and construction. I have worked as a research assistant in Cryptocurrency and Blockchain Technologies, also in data analysis, NLP and artificial intelligence. I'm interested in projects that involve BigData, statistics, ML and Data Science, and above all with a social focus.

Experience

October 2020 - August 2021, RAPPI

Data Engineer

Details: Data engineer at RAPPIBANK, giving general business support in everything related to RAPPIBANK data for LATAM, this implies presenting solutions, proposals, and elaboration of pipelines.

April 2020 - September 2020, CIUP

Data Scientist

Details: I collaborated in research projects for World Bank, all results where published in **Analysis of the Health Network of Metropolitan Lima Against Large-Scale Earthquakes**; and PCM (Contact Tracing, and analysis of the probability of contagion of covid19 based on their interactions).

December 2019 - February 2020, BWIT

Big Data Engineer, Data Scientist

Details: Liderando construcción de un módulo de clasificación, de transacciones (Rubros) para el sector bancario, las tecnologías empleadas fueron Python, AWS, Nifi, Hadoop, Hive, Teradata y códigos Bash.

August 2019 - November 2019, INDRA

Big Data Engineer

Details: Leading the design and development of a transaction classification module (Items) for the banking sector, the technologies used were Python, AWS, Nifi, Hadoop, Hive, Teradata and Bash codes.

Research Center of Pacific University 2018 - February 2019

Research assistant on Data Scientist

Leading researchers: M. Nuñez del prado, Ph.D y H. Alatrista S., Ph.D. Details: I contributed by analyzing and mining of customer buying behaviors using unsupervised methods (machine learning) and NLP.

March 2017 - 2018

Research Assistant

Leading researcher: F. Rosales M., Ph.D.

Details: Research projects on Blockchain, creation of a cryptocurrency

from a Bitcoin fork.

Dapps development on the Ethereum platform, as well as web application development through API. Development of algorithms in R and Julia languages.

May 2018 - May 2019, Everis S.A

Big Data, Solutions Assistant.

Details: I collaborated in Big Data projects of some Peruvian banks with technologies from the Apache community, databricks, cassandra, kafka among others. I received training in Big Data, Hadoop, Hive, Spark, Sqoop, Kafka, zookeper and HBase; and create multiple proofs of concepts.

August 2017 - December 2017, ONPE-GSFP

System engineer Passant

Details: I collaborated with the Cleaning and validation (ETL) of data from the reports of the political organizations, for their later storage and use, this process included, in addition to a cleaning and correction of data validated with the RENIEC Database, a verification and user confirmation (errors were reported by eminent ones).

Education

2020 - Today, San Marcos University

Faculty of Mathematical Sciences

Master's student in mathematical statistics

2012 - 2017, San Marcos University

Faculty of Systems Engineering

Bachelor of Systems Engineering

Spring - 2016, Chile University

Faculty of Economics and Business

Exchange Student (Pacific Alliance Scholarship)

Skills

Big Data and Cloud Tools

- Hadoop, Hive, NIFI shift, Lambda, sage Hbase, Scoop GCP (Dataproc, maker, Athena)
 Spark Dataflow, BigQuery, Azure (Databriks, Blob
- Kafka CloudStorage) Storage)
- o Airflow, Astronomer o AWS (S3, Red-

Methodologies and platforms

- RUP, Scrum, XP
 Model Canvas (*)
 TCP/IP, VPN
- Design ThinkingLinux-Windows

Computer programs

- Programming languages (Java, Scala, Python, R, Julia, C/C++).
- Office Tools (Office LibreOffice).
- RapidMiner, SPSS-Modeler and Python for Business Intelligence.
- Development Frameworks (MySql, Teradata, Postgres, Oracle, SqlServer, MongoDB).
- o Rational Rose y bizagi modeler.

Additional Information

Publications

SIMBig2020

Analysis of the Health Network of Metropolitan Lima Against Large-Scale Earthquake ISBN:978-3-030-76228-5.

Achievements

- Ex-Fellow of the Pacific Alliance in Chile
- Hackspace Hackathon: Contact Tracing 2020 Winning Project
- IBM CODING DAY: HACKATHON POR UN PERÚ SINANEMIA Winning Project
- HACKATHON ARTTEC Winning Project

Languages

- English (Advanced studying)Spanish (Native)
- Portuguese (Basic)

Projects

- **PCM MINSA** Contact Tracing Peru in your hands.
- WorldBank Analysis of the health network in the event of earthquakes.
- VacBs Creation of a mobile App for people on hand milk production with INIA, UP, UALM; This project involved the use of Neural Networks. Informative note.
- **EsanCoin/CiupCoin** CCreation of a Cryptocurrency for educational purposes, based on the source code of bitcoin and learncoin from which we fork, video tutorial here.
- Rocket/Black Rabbits Get Lost In The Woods Creation of a Dapp on the Ethereum Blockchain platform.